<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The desires of the States of Scotland to the Parliament of England concerning, His Majesties advancing from Newcastle towards the city of London, with their deserting of the garrisons of Newcastle and Tinmouth, and Major Gen: Skippon to take possession of them. Likewise the proceedings of the Parliaments Commissioners at Newcastle, and his Majesties propositions to the Scots Lords, about his departure from thence.</title>
            <title>Proceedings. 1647</title>
            <author>Scotland. Convention of Estates.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92558</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S1230</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E372_16</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201318</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896088</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896088</idno>
            <idno type="VID">154069</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92558)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 154069)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2396:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The desires of the States of Scotland to the Parliament of England concerning, His Majesties advancing from Newcastle towards the city of London, with their deserting of the garrisons of Newcastle and Tinmouth, and Major Gen: Skippon to take possession of them. Likewise the proceedings of the Parliaments Commissioners at Newcastle, and his Majesties propositions to the Scots Lords, about his departure from thence.</title>
                  <title>Proceedings. 1647</title>
                  <author>Scotland. Convention of Estates.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for E, A, [sic],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>January 28! [1647]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from Wing (CD-ROM edition).</note>
                  <note>A narrative.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "1646".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:154069:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 85 -->
            <p>THE DESIRES Of the States of SCOTLAND To the PARLIAMENT of ENGLAND: <hi>CONCERNING,</hi> His Majeſties advancing from <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the City of <hi>London,</hi> with their deſerting of the Garriſons of Newcaſtle and Tinmouth, and Major Gen: Skippon to take poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſesſion of them.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe the proceedings of the Parliaments Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners at Newcaſtle, And his Majeſties Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions to the Scots Lords, about his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture from thence.</p>
            <p>Printed for <hi>E, A,</hi> January 28!</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:154069:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 86 -->
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="proceedings">
            <pb facs="tcp:154069:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 87 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:154069:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 87 -->
            <head>A TRVE RELATION OF The Proceedings of the Parliaments Commiſſioners at Newcaſtle.</head>
            <p>THE great Argument which holds the Kingdom in Diſputation &amp; Suſpence, is, the diſpoſall of his Majeſties perſon <hi>(great Brittains Soveraign)</hi> a thing (indeed) of great concernment; yet all muſt be referred to the moſt wiſe and ſerious conſideration of the great Councels of both Kingdomes; whoſe
<pb facs="tcp:154069:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 88 -->gallant concurrence, and mutuall amity, will (no doubt) in a ſhort time, ſettle and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh the Subjects of both Nations, in a moſt firme and glorious peace.</p>
            <p>For no Coles of Wrath can be kindled within the hearts of the Engliſh and Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Commiſſioners (although many great Ones have indeavoured to ſtirre up the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers) but go on with alacrity, for the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging of that great <hi>truſt,</hi> committed to their charge, by the Eſtates of both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes.</p>
            <p>For upon the two and twentieth day of this inſtant moneth of January, the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments Commiſſioners arrived ſafe at New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſtle, being entertained with much joy and tryumph, and the Scottiſh Commiſſioners have expreſſed themſelves gallantly unto them, ſhewing their great forwardneſſe, to comply with them, and expedite the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, for which they came about, being reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, not to adhere (in the leaſt) to any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular that ſhal prove prejudiciall to either Kingdoms; and therefore, doe freely aſſent and concur with them, that his Majeſty ſhal come to Holmby houſe, or any other place
<pb facs="tcp:154069:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 88 -->that the Parliament of England ſhall make choice of, and there continue untill he ſhall ſubſcribe unto the Propoſitions.</p>
            <p>And it is likewiſe declared from the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of Scotland, that they deſire there may be a Committee of both Kingdoms con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly to attend his Majeſty, to uſe their ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt endeavours for perſwading of his Maj. to paſſe the Propoſitions, and to advance the union betwixt both Kingdoms. Further in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timating their deſires, that thoſe who ſhall be employed on the buſineſſe of State from that Kingdom may have due acceſſe unto his Majeſty, after their reſigning of Him up to the Parliament of England; deſiring alſo, Brotherly aſſiſtance againſt all foes domeſtic or forraign, and particularly, againſt thoſe barbarous Rebels now in their Kingdome.</p>
            <p>The Scottiſh Forces are (almoſt) upon a martch with their bag and baggage, ſome of their Carriages being drawn out of Newca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, and their great Ordnance diſmounted and ready to be ſhipt for Scotland.</p>
            <p>The Earle of Stamford is appointed to ſee all things fairly carryed, and the articles
<pb facs="tcp:154069:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 89 -->faithfully maintained, upon the Scots delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Northern Gariſons.</p>
            <p>Major General Skippon is to place a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient ſtrength in the Garriſons of Newca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle and Tinmouth, and to remaine Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</p>
            <p>The King is expected Southwards dayly, &amp; divers of the Scottiſh Nobility and Gentry (is thought will accompany him.</p>
            <p>But his Maieſty is ſomwhat perplexed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the reſigning up of Newcaſtle, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding to the Nobility of Scotland, as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth:</p>
            <q>IT is a received opinion by many, that ingagements, acts or promiſes of a reſtrained perſon, are neither valid nor obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory; How true or falſe this is, I wil not diſpute; but I am ſure, if I am not free, I am not fit to anſwer your or any Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions: Wherefore you ſhould firſt reſolve me in what ſtate <hi>I</hi> ſtand (as in relation to freedom) before I can give you any other anſwer (the reaſon of this my queſtion, the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour can beſt reſolve you) But if you object the loſſe of time and urgency of it; certainly in one reſpect it preſſes none ſo much as my ſelf, which makes me alſo think it neceſſary, that I be not to ſeek what to do when this Gariſon ſhal be ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendred up, to demand of you, in caſe <hi>I</hi> go into <hi>Scotland,</hi> if <hi>I</hi> ſhal be there with honour, freedom, and ſafety, or how? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ready to give you a farther and more particular anſwer, how ſoon you ſhal have reſolved theſe two Queres.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>The Scots Commiſſioners Anſwer te his Majeſties Quaeres Ian.</hi> 14.</p>
            <q>
               <p n="1">1. To the firſt, in what ſtate you ſtand, as in relation ro freedom, the Parliaments of both your Kingdoms have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb facs="tcp:154069:5"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 89 -->ſuch orders and directions as they have thought fitteſt for the good and ſafety of your Majeſty and the Kingdoms, to the General and Governour.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To your Majeſties ſecond Quaere, of your going into Scotland, we ſhal humbly deſire, that we may not be now put to give any Anſwer; but if your Majeſty ſhal either deny or delay your aſſent to the Propoſitions, we are in that caſe to repreſent to your Majeſty the Reſolutions of the Parliament of England.</p>
            </q>
            <p>His Maieſties Reply.</p>
            <q>I know very wel, that the Gen. and Governour have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved orders concerning me; but the queſtion is, into what ſtate thoſe Orders put me in (as relating to freedome) To which you have either power to anſwer, or not; if you have, then anſwer me: otherwiſe ſend to thoſe who can: And ſo to my ſecond quere.</q>
            <p>The great Politician Doctor Hudſon were brought to the Parliament houſe, and called in before the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, who examined him whether he had beene with the King (ſince his eſcape at Newcaſtle<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, And it was further demanded of him, whether he wrote to Major Generall Laughorn, and whether it were not to perſwade him to decline the Parliament, which he alſo acknowledged: The houſe proceeded further in examination of him, which was too long to be inſerted in this ſheet, but when that was done, they came to this reſult, that hee was charged with treaſon, and it was ordered that the ſaid <hi>Mr.</hi> Hudſon ſhall bee ſent forth with to the Tower of London, there to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main cloſe priſoner, and that none ſhall ſpeake with him but in the preſence of his Keeper.</p>
            <p>Letters were preſented to the Houſe of Commons coming from beyond Sea, which tell of ſtrange ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, how true wee know not, but the relation comes from a good hand.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:154069:6"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 90 -->
            <p>One is a letter from Poland, ſpeaking plainly that the great Aſſembly or Parliament of that Kingdome have put their King under reſtraint for raiſing of for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces without their conſent.</p>
            <p>That they told him freely in open Parliament, he had forfeited his Crown, and that all his ſubjects are thereby diſcharged of their Allegeance, and are not to be further ſubject to his commands, That they have commanded the Kings Seal not to be any longer uſed and raiſed a Guard of twelve hundred to attend the King, and keep the Kingdom in Peace.</p>
            <p>One cauſe of the difference between the King of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land and his ſubjects, is ſaid to be, his endeavor to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue a warre contrary to the advice of the States and Councel of that Kingdom, and againſt the mind of the Lord Marſhall.</p>
            <p>We ſhall now conclude with what we have laſt from the North from whence is our greateſt expectation of Newes as affaires ſtand. The money is gone from York, Northalerton is 22 miles beyond, where the firſt hundred thouſand pound is paid, Our Commiſsioners are come to Newcaſtle, and faire congratulations be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Commiſsioners of Scotland and them, and ſome Conference.</p>
            <p>They alſo apply themſelves to his Majeſty, who ſeemes to be hardly perſwaded to come to Holmby houſe: what wil follow, few dayes will evidence: but our Commiſſioners being newly come thither, it could now produce little, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept what is before.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
